Sesquicentennial Celebration Records, circa 1887-1993 (bulk 1894-1904 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Sesquicentennial Celebration Records
circa 1887-1993
1894-1904
AC141
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Seeley G. Mudd Manuscript Library. Princeton University Archives. 65 Olden Street Princeton, New Jersey 08540 USA
6.02 linear feet 2 archival boxes, 1 half-size archival box, 3 flat 11" x 9" x 1.5" archival boxes, 1 25" x 30" x 3" archival box, and 10 custom boxes
Sesquicentennial Celebration Committee.
The collection consists of materials relating to the three-day Sesquicentennial Celebration in October 1896, at which the College of New Jersey became Princeton University. In addition to ephemera and printed material distributed at the celebration, the collection includes a typescript draft of President Francis Landey Patton's sermon, sesquicentennial memorial books, a published sketchbook, official congratulations from other institutions, and press releases and newspaper clippings reporting the events.
The celebration of the College's 150th anniversary in October 1896 was an event over two years in the making. By all accounts, it was a great success. Participants long remembered the eloquent speeches made by former U.S. President Grover Cleveland and future U.S. President Woodrow Wilson and the procession of torch-carrying Princetonians that marched through town to a Nassau Hall covered with orange electric lights. The culminating announcement came from College President Francis Landey Patton when he declared that “what heretofore for one hundred fifty years has been known as the College of New Jersey shall in all future time be known as Princeton University.”
The three-day Sesquicentennial Celebration included hundreds of undergraduates, thousands of alumni, representatives from universities throughout the world, distinguished European scholars, and delegations of students from other colleges and universities. The College and the town were decorated everywhere with red, white, and blue, and orange and black banners; the College erected an arched gateway at one end of Nassau Street, while the town put up a matching gateway at the other end. Princeton won the sesquicentennial football game against Virginia, 48-0. In addition to Grover Cleveland and then Professor Woodrow Wilson, speakers at the celebration included several European scholars, the poet and professor Henry van Dyke, the president of Harvard, Charles Eliot, and the College's own president, Francis Landey Patton.
The collection is arranged in five series as follows:
Collection is open for research use.
Compiled by the Sesquicentennial Celebration Committee and the University Library. The third scrapbook in Series 4 and the contents of Series 3 were donated to the Library in June 1904 by the Rev. George Blackburn Kinkead III, Class of 1899.
Other materials relating to the Princeton Sesquicentennial Celebration can be found in the P Collection and in the University Library's general catalogue.
Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Kinkead, George Blackburn.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Princeton University -- Centennial celebrations, etc.; Princeton University -- History -- 19th century.; Autographs.; Scrapbooks.; Corespondence.; Printing plates.; Princeton University
- Celebration Materials, circa 1887-1993; 20 folders
  Celebration Materials, circa 1887-1993, collects invitations, programs, mass mailings, event notices, pins, and correspondence relating to the celebration (similar materials can be found in the first scrapbook in Series 4). A typed draft of President Francis Landey Patton's sesquicentennial sermon with corrections, a photograph album of the event, and a published book of sketches from the celebration by William Silas Whitehead can be found in this series as well.
  - Clippings, circa 1887-1946; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commemorative Medal Information, 1900-1993; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Handbook of Princeton, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Invitations, Programs, and Tickets, 1896 September-October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Patton, Francis L. “Religion and the University.” Sesquicentennial Sermon, Original Typescript Copy with Corrections, 1896; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Excursion Tickets Flyer Photocopy, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Excursion Tickets Flyer Original, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Preparation for the Events, 1894 November-1896 August; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publication Information, circa 1896 December; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Torchlight Procession Information, 1896 September-October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Van Wagenen, George A. Sesquicentennial Photograph Album, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Whitehead, William Silas, Jr. Sketches: Princeton Sesquicentennial Celebration, 1896; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Acknowledgments for Memorial Book, 1898-1899; 1 folder (Box 16)
  - Letter from Raymond Hastings Alleyne Carter, Princeton Class of 1899, to His Father Describing Sesquicentennial Celebrations, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 16)
  - Committee on Reception and Entertainment, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 16)
    Includes Survey of Rooms in Princeton Conducted Spring 1896
  - Printed Ephemera, circa 1896; 1 folder (Box 16)
  - Sesquicentennial Badges, circa 1896; 1 envelope (Box 16)
  - Sesquicentennial Miscellaneous, circa 1896; 1 folder (Box 16)
  - Sesquicentennial Newspaper Clippings, circa 1896; 1 folder (Box 16)
- Institutional Congratulations, 1896-1899; 49 folders
  Institutional Congratulations, 1896-1899, includes official congratulations issued to Princeton by colleges, universities, and academic societies around the world. While some were written in Latin, on vellum, or in calligraphy, others were merely written longhand to acknowledge receipt of an invitation from the sesquicentennial organizing committee. Congratulatory documents from Athens, Dartmouth, Paris, Rutgers, Tokyo, and Zurich are especially notable. Documents are sorted alphabetically by institution except for the oversize documents, which are all grouped together.
  - List of Institutional Congratulations, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Aberdeen, University of, 1896 June; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alliance of Reformed Churches, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Athens, University of, 1899; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bombay, University of, 1896 July; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brussels, University of, 1898 December; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - California, University of, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Christiania, University of, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Colonial Wars, Society of, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Copenhagen, University of, 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dartmouth College, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Erlangen, University of, 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Giessen, University of, 1896 June; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Groningen, University of, 1896 July; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Haverford College, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Heidelberg University, 1896 June; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hobart College, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Jena, University of, 1896 September-1898 December; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Kaiser Wilhelms Universitat, 1896 August; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Koniglich Wurtembergischen Universitat, Tubingen, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lick Observatory, University of California, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Melbourne, University of, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - New York University, 1896 November; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Paris, University of, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Pennsylvania College, 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Queen's College, Belfast, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Queens College and University, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Rostok, University of, 1896 September; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Rutgers College, 1896 November; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Southwestern Presbyterian University, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Swarthmore College, 1896 June; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Syrian Protestant College, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Texas, University of, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Tokyo, University of, 1897 September; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Union University, 1896 August; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - United States Military Academy, 1896 May; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - United States Naval Academy, 1896 April; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Vanderbilt University, 1896 September; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Victoria University, circa 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Washington University, Missouri, 1896 October; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Washington and Lee University, 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Western Reserve University, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Williams College, 1896 June; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Wisconsin, University of, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Zurich, University of, 1896 March; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Oversize Institutional Congratulations, circa 1896; 3 folders (Box 17, Folders 2-4)
- Memorial Book Autograph Edition Correspondence, 1896-1904; 22 folders
  Memorial Book Autograph Edition Correspondence, 1896-1904, consists of the correspondence between the Rev. George Blackburn Kinkead III, Class of 1899, and participants in the Sesquicentennial Celebration for the purpose of acquiring their signatures. Kinkead pasted the autographs in a Sesquicentennial Celebration memorial book (Box 15) and donated it to the Library in 1904. Material in this series is sorted according to the last initial of the correspondent.
  - A, 1900 January-1903 September; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - B, 1896 October-1904 April; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - C, 1899 March-1904 May; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - D, 1899 October-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - E, 1896 October-1903 September; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - F, 1902 September-1904 February; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - G, 1896 March-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - H, 1899 November-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - I, 1903 June; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - J, 1899 December-1903 September; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - K, 1899 September-1904 January; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - L, 1896 May-1903 December; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - M, 1899 September-1904 October; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - N, O, 1899 November-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - P, 1899 March-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - R, 1899 October-1904 June; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - S, 1896 May-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - T, 1899 July-1904 February; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - V, 1902 October; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - W, 1899 October-1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Y, 1904 March; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Indecipherable, 1896 September-1904; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Scrapbooks, 1896-1897; 7 boxes
  Scrapbooks, 1896-1897, contains seven volumes stored in boxes. The first contains ephemera relating to the celebration, such as invitations, tickets, notices, class newsletters, and press releases. The other volumes hold newspaper clippings about the celebration. These volumes are repetitive because most newspapers chose to reprint the news releases in full. There are, however, some original articles, illustrations, and notices regarding the Sesquicentennial Celebration; and clippings from newspapers throughout the country are represented.
  - Volume 1, 1896 February-1897 February; 1 box (Box 3)
  - Volume 2, 1896 August-October; 1 box (Box 4)
  - Volume 3, 1896 August-October; 1 box (Box 5)
  - Volume 4, 1896 October; 1 box (Box 6)
  - Volume 5, 1896 October; 1 box (Box 7)
  - Volume 6, 1896 October-December; 1 box (Box 8)
  - Volume 7, 1896 September-1897 March; 1 box (Box 9)
- Memorial Book Engravers' Plates, 1898; 3 boxes
  Memorial Book Engravers' Plates, 1898, consists of the engraved plates used to print the illustrations in the memorial book published in that year. Illustrations include portraits of the College's presidents, prominent or new buildings, and an image of the sesquicentennial torchlight procession with former U.S. President Grover Cleveland in the foreground. The plates are arranged alphabetically by subject. The boxes containing the plates are very heavy. Researchers should use care when handling.
  - Alexander Hall, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Blair Hall, 1898; 2 folders (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Brown Hall, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Burr, Aaron, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Carnahan, James, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Chancellor Green Library, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Davies, Samuel, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Dickinson, Jonathan, 1898; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Edwards, Jonathan, 1898; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Finley, Samuel, 1898; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Green, Ashbel, 1898; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Lower Pyne Dormitory, 1898; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Maclean, John, 1898; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Nassau Hall, 1898; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Patton, Francis Landey, 1898; 2 folders (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
  - Prospect House, 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Pyne Library, 1898; 2 folders (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - Pyne Library Courtyard, 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Smith, Samuel Stanhope, 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Torchlight Parade (October 20, 1896), 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Upper Pyne Dormitory, 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Whig and Clio Halls, 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Witherspoon, John, 1898; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Memorial Books, 1898; 3 boxes
  Memorial Books, 1898, includes three memorial books whose purpose was to document the Sesquicentennial Celebration. The first volume is unaltered. The second has been enhanced with original documents, particularly those containing the autographs of the College's former presidents and officials involved with the Sesquicentennial Celebration. Hundreds of autographs (almost entirely by people present at the celebration) have been added to the third volume.
  - Princeton Sesquicentennial Celebration Memorial Book, 1898; 1 box (Box 13)
  - Princeton Sesquicentennial Celebration Memorial Book, with Documents Added until 1907, 1898; 1 box (Box 14)
  - Princeton Sesquicentennial Celebration Memorial Book, with Autographs Added until 1904, 1898; 1 box (Box 15)